MATTHEW P. MOMJIAN

matthew@momjian.me

Philadelphia, PA https://momjian.me

STATEMENT OF PURPOSE

I am a first-year medical student with extensive experience in pre-hospital medical care and a dedication to learning, teaching, and leading through my diverse interests and talents. Providing emergency medical care in a high-volume urban environment has given me a deeper understanding of modern healthcare challenges. My current focus is on increasing my exposure to a variety of medical specialties. Future goals include practicing as an Emergency Physician in a metropolitan area.

EDUCATION

Philadelphia College of Osteopathic Medicine, Doctor of Osteopathic Medicine

2020 - Present

Franklin & Marshall College, Bachelor of Arts in Music

2010 - 2014

Cum Laude, Departmental Honors in Music, Honors List (x5), Dean's List, Marshall Fellow
Independent Study: "Conducting Performance of Beethoven's Symphony No. 3, Richard Yardumian's
Armenian Suite." Adviser: Dr. Brian H. Norcross, DMA

PROFESSIONAL LICENSES, TRAINING, AND AFFILIATIONS

Emergency Medical Technician - licensed by Pennsylvania, Delaware, and the National Registry

Bleeding Control Instructor - American College of Surgeons Committee on Trauma

Pre-Hospital Trauma Life Support Instructor – National Association of EMTs

Tactical Combat Casualty Care Instructor - Joint Trauma System, Department of Defense

CPR Instructor and Advanced Cardiac Life Support Provider - American Heart Association

EMS Today Conference & Competition – Journal of Emergency Medical Services

Attended annual industry conference covering innovative pre-hospital medical care.

Competed in EMS skills competition and placed highly multiple times, served as Team Captain.

Resuscitation Academy - Global Resuscitation Alliance

Intensive course focusing on the latest innovations in cardiac arrest treatment and care.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Saint Francis Healthcare, Wilmington, DE

2012 - 2020

Field Training Officer, Emergency Medical Technician III (Senior EMT)

Provide emergency ambulance care in a busy metropolitan system.

Precepted over 20 new EMTs through a three-month field internship program.

Operate as an individual provider in the role of acting supervisor, managing eight units.

Teach annual departmental courses and proctor oral and practical boards.

COMMUNITY SERVICE

Marple Township Ambulance Corps, Broomall, PA

2011 - Present

Secretary of the Board, Field Training Officer, EMT

Volunteer at local ambulance service covering suburban Philadelphia, over 2,500 hours to date.

Work with paramedics providing advanced life support.

Teach public CPR courses as lead instructor, assist with public outreach and education.

Franklin & Marshall College Emergency Medical Services, Lancaster, PA

2011 - 2014

Director of Emergency Medical Services, Chief of Operations, EMT

Supervised squad of twenty members and created, proposed, and managed budget.

Coordinated and led education for new and continuing members.

Addressed personnel issues and created member awards to improve retention.

Greater Philadelphia Homeschool Science Fair, Villanova, PA

February 2014 & 2015

Judged various grades at local science fair.

Armenian Missionary Association of America, Armenia

July 2012

Two-week mission and service trip to rural Armenia. Led religious summer camps and activities.

Proclamation Presbyterian Church, Dominican Republic

June 2010

Ten-day mission and service trip. Assisted with religious summer camp and provided manual labor.

HONORS AND AWARDS

Unit Citation, Saint Francis Healthcare Emergency Medical Services

2018

Given for outstanding patient care during a difficult event in the community.

Individual Citation, New Castle County Department of Public Safety

2015 - 2017

Given for the successful pre-hospital resuscitation and discharge of a cardiac arrest patient.

Exceptional Duty, Marple Township Ambulance Corps

2015

Given for significant hours dedicated in service to the organization.

Winner, Pennsylvania Department of Health, HeartRescue Project

2014

Created original video used to educate state EMTs in new "pit crew" resuscitation techniques.

Unit Citation, Saint Francis Healthcare Emergency Medical Services

2014

Given for the successful pre-hospital resuscitation and discharge of a cardiac arrest patient.

Nolt Music Award, Franklin & Marshall College

2014

Given by the music department to recognize outstanding students and support original research.

General Chemistry Award, Franklin & Marshall College

2011

Awarded by the chemistry department to recognize exceptional performance across both semesters.

PRESENTATIONS, RESEARCH, AND TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Research	CITE PAPER, Philadelphia College of Osteopathic Medicine.	20	20
Research	Developed and wrote protocols for fly genetics lab for future biology classes, Franklin & Marshall College Department of Biology.	20)12
Presentation	"Report on Mission Trip to Armenia," Armenian Martyrs' Congregational Church.	20)12
Coaching	Robotics Summer Competitions, Broomall, PA.	2008 - 20	11
Workshop	"Introduction to 3D Rendering with Blender," O'Reilly Open Source Convention.	20	10

LANGUAGES

Native: English, Armenian

SKILLS, HOBBIES, AND INTERESTS

My travels to nearly 30 countries have increased my appreciation for many distinct cultures and traditions. I enjoy many outdoor activities such as kayaking, hiking, swimming, and marksmanship. When I am not outside, I have developed skills in computer programming, have competed on robotics teams at an international level, and play multiple musical instruments. As a first generation American and U.S. citizen, my Armenian ethnicity is particularly important to me, and I continuously strive to bring my Armenian culture to my everyday life.